Finding Aid for War of 1812 Collection
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- War of 1812 collection
  - 1814 March 7. Sir Phineas Riall ALS to Sir Gordon Drummond; Niagara Frontier., 2 pages; Intelligence of military defeat [the Battle of Longwoods]; encloses a report made by Captain [Alexander] Stewart. "I regret to say that our loss has been very great considering the Numbers we had engaged, and that notwithstanding the Gallantry displayed on the occasion they were obliged to retire owing to the very superior Force of the enemy." Folder includes a one-page ADS return of casualties from Alexander Stewart dated March 5, 1814.
  - 1814 March 10. R[uggles] Hubbard ALS to Thomas H. Hubbard; Albany, [New York]., 3 pages; Anti-Federalist, Hawkish political sentiments; "I eat no 'dirty bread…from the Stagnant pools & ditche of the Commonwealth' and am a minute man to take up arms as before against Madison and in favour of a Northern President."
  - 1814 March 11. James Simpson ALS to William R. Smith; Huntingdon., 1 page; List of militia men in the Second Company of the 33rd Regiment who failed to perform military service; "who being notified to meet at Alexandria on the thirteenth of April 1813 to perform a tour of Duty in Service of the united States and Did not perform Said tour nor Send Substitutes."
  - 1814 March 21. Joseph Loring DS to Samuel Hodges; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 2 pages; Orders addressed to Lt. Hodges and Lt. Manning; Hodges will relieve Lt. Lewis until further orders, and Manning will proceed with recruits to Captain Tillebrown's Company and eventually join a force under the command of Major Putnam. Includes orders to other men.
  - 1814 March 26. Will Williams DS to [James] McCloskey; Detroit., 1 page; Requesting the bearer of the note be paid twelve dollars "for forty two pounds of sugar for the use of the Hospital." Signed by Will Williams, Hosp[ita]l Surg[eon] Mate. With United States DS to Kebiasse; Detroit; 1 page; March 26, 1814. Receipt for $12 paid by the United States government to "Kebiasse an indian" for 42 pounds of sugar to be used in the Detroit hospital. Acknowledges receipt of the money from James McCloskey, A[ssistant] D[eputy] Q[uarter] M[aster] G[e]n[era]l. Includes Kebiasse's mark, witnessed by John Roby.
  - 1814 April 9. Alexander Macomb ALS to Thomas Macdonough., 2 pages; News from General Wilkinson; he has been informed "that the enimy meditate some enterprizes on the lake with their flotilla." Requests that Macdonough inform him of his situation and he will try to protect him from the enemy's enterprizes. He can bring 1000 men into the field in case of attack. (Box 4)
  - 1814 April 13. United States Treasury Pr. DS to Richard Cairns., 1 page; Pay of Richard Cairns, a corporal in Captain Joseph Cairns' Company of the 27th U.S. Infantry Regiment. He was "regularly discharged on the 6th day of April 1814 his term of service having expired on the 29th day of March 1814."
  - 1814 April 19. Edmund Pendleton Gaines ALS to Dr. Thomas; Sackett's Harbor, [New York]., 2 pages; Orders to report to Major Hindman of the 2nd Artillery to serve as surgeon "until he shall be supplied with a surgeon or s. mate."
  - 1814 April 25. John Armstrong LS to William Jones; War Department., 2 pages; Regarding Detroit and Michigan, army movements; "Should the Enemy reinstate himself on the Eastern-banks of the Detroit and the Huron - it's return would necessarily be much jeopardized. On the 27th Ultimo there was no force of the Enemy within 130 miles of the Detroit."
  - May 7, 1814. James Gibson ALS to Callender Irvine; Lancaster, [Pennsylvania]., 1 page; Drawing money from the banks; he sends a check for Captain Irvine for $4,500, "which I wish him to get in American gold or Eastern Notes, as I am informed that Drafts on the Banks in [Philadelphia], or Notes, will not pass among the Yankees without a discount." Inquires on the best way to send him the money should he have already left Philadelphia.
  - 1814 May 13. Alexander Neef ALS to Andrew W. Bell; Cantonment Plattsburg [New York]., 3 pages; Account of his expedition into Canada; "the British fleet have Gone towards the head of the lake, probably their intention is to Blockade our fleet…" He describes the make-up of both British and American forces, and expects American victory on the lake is the force is ready for the lake. Expects to be ordered to the recruitment service soon.
  - 1814 May 26. Lemuel Trescott DS to Francis Haskell; District of Passamaquody, [Maine]., 1 page; Document certifying Haskell's American citizenship.
  - 1814 May 28. Samuel Franklin ADS; Portland, [Maine]., 1 page; List of British prisoners on the schooner Mammoth.
  - 1814 May 31. John Armstrong, Jr. LS to Isaac Shelby; War Department., 1 page; Shelby has been appointed a commission to treat Cass with North Western Native American’s; "In this mission you will be associated with General Harrison and Governor [Lewis] ." Harrison will decide the time and place for the commission to meet with them, "and you will please to communicate with him for that purpose."
  - 1814 June 3. Samuel Franklin DS; Portland, [Maine]., 2 pages; Report of British prisoners brought to Portland by the schooner Mammoth, "whereof Samuel Franklin is master." Includes such information as name, rank, from what vessel captured, and national affiliation.
  - 1814 June 16. Alexander Neef ALS to Andrew W. Bell; Champlain., 3 pages; Eyewitness account of the Second Battle of Lacolle Mills; "the enemy were completely vanquish'd, and only waited a summons from our Genl. to have surrendered…"
  - 1814 June 19. Sir Phineas Riall ALS to Sir Gordon Drummond; Fort George., 1 page; Captain Norton has requested that wampum to be transmitted to "His Excellency the [Commander] of the Forces." Includes a 4-page ALS report of affairs from Riall [to Drummond] regarding Upper Canada and relations with Five Nations
  - 1814 June 20 to 1814 December 20. Andrew Jackson ADS; Fayetteville, [Tennessee]., 1 page; Muster Roll of a company under James Blackemore.
  - 1814 June 21. John Armstrong, Jr. LS to John H. Piatt; War Department., 1 page; Referring to him request for supplies for prisoners of war; "The Commisary General for Prisoners of War has applied to this Department to furnish rations for the prisoners on their march to the frontier, and has been referred to you for such suplies as he may require - the amount of which must be charged to him, as the prisoners are not supplied by this Department."
  - 1814 June 24. Abel Boynton ALS; S[ackett's] Harbor, [New York]., 1 page; Concerning the paying of troops and debts, and references the British blockade.
  - 1814 June 25. John H. Sheppard ALS to Mrs. S. Sheppard; Wiscasset, [Maine]., 3 pages; Discusses English prisoners brought to town and the inability of the British to land; there is "general alarm excited on this coast & particularly…by English Ships & barges." Includes a small map.
  - 1814 July 7. George Izard ALS to Thomas A. Smith; Camp near Plattsburg, [New York]., 1 page; Concerning Col. Tobias Lear, commissioned to arrange a prisoner exchange. The British commander that he is supposed to meet with "has been delayed at Albany, but will probably arrive in the Course of two or three days..." He is surprised that he has not seen more deserters.
  - [1814 July 11]. Ms. Cy; Eastport, [Maine]., 2 pages; Article of Capitulation for the surrender of Moose Island, Maine.
  - 1814 July 16. Richard W. Lawrence AL to John L. Lawrence; Lisbon, Portugal., 3 pages; Concerning the forthcoming Congress of Ghent; "As a young Diplomatist it would be certainly very desirable to be present at the Congress at Ghent; but it is apprehended here by many of our Countrymen that out Commisioners will have little else to do in that business than to sign such a Treaty as their opponent may think proper to form for them..."
  - 1814 July 22. Samuel Dickinson DS to Elijah Dickinson; Bermuda., 9 pages; Regarding loss of the schooner Swan & Eliza; also includes an invoice of goods shipped on board the ship dated January 16, 1814.
  - 1814 July 26. Eben[ezer] Judd ALS to Hubbard Grave., 1 page; Beacon light warning system has been ordered by the Captain General to be set up in case of British attack; he mentions them being set up in multiple towns along the sea board, including Long Hill [Connecticut].
  - 1814 July 27, 1814 September 15, and 1815 March 2. John Le Counter 3 ALsS to William Robinson; Queenston, Chippewa, and Montréal, [Quebec]., 11 pages; Regarding the Battle of Lundy’s Lane.
  - 1814 August 7. Sir Henry Edward Bunbury ACyS to Lord Bathurst., 8 pages; Bunbury, the Under-Secretary of State for War and the Colonies, provides his reasons for objecting to the proposed expedition to New Orleans; "I now venture to submit to you…the principal reasons which incline me to think that it would be better & safer for The King's Service that the Enterprize should be deferred."
  - 1814 August 10. J[oseph] Williamson ALS to Norman Williams; Bangor, [Maine]., 3 pages; People of Maine anxious for peace suffering from blockade. Coastal towns threatened with invasion. Comments on Brown’s victory and mentions that "I have but little hopes of peace since the downfall of Bonaparte."
  - 1814 August 20. Nathaniel Taylor ALS to Patrick Taylor; Kingston, [Ontario]., 4 pages; Describes march under hard conditions from Montreal to Kingston; "the Commander of the Forces was at Montreal when we arrived & saw us next morning in a field adjaecent to the Town: it is a large papulous fine Town with good streets & regular: plenty of everything but the war makes all things extremely dear."
  - 1814 August 30. [Manuel Eyre] ADf to [William Jones]., 5 pages; Report and resolutions from the Committee for the Defense of Philadelphia; "we are authorized to call upon you for such aid in resisting any attack from the enemy as will be consistent with the duties of your department to grant considering the aid of Naval resources and the personal services of the Officers seamen & Marines..."
  - 1814 August 30. Edmund Palmer ALS to John Wilson Croker; HMS Hebrus on the Patuxent [Maryland]., 2 pages; Regarding the burning of War Department in Washington and a model of field magazine saved from destruction; "At the destruction of the public Works at Washington, it fell to me to burn the War Office, and amongst two or three things which I saved from the flames, is the accompanying model, which appears to be intended as a kind of field magazine for powder."
  - [post 1814 August]. Schuylkill and ---- Counties, [Pennsylvania] Df; [Pennsylvania]., 3 pages; Meeting minutes; draft of resolutions regarding British depredations and county offices, decries the conduct of the British military, particularly in the burning of Washington. Resolutions include establishing a Committee of Correspondence and the election of "two Candidates for Congress, eight Candidates, for the General Assembly of this Commonwealth and six Candidates for Auditors of this County."
  - 1814 September 1. National Intelligence Pr. Document; Washington, D.C., 4 pages; 1870s newspaper of material related to War of 1812 taken from a National Intelligence Officer. Includes an account of the capture of Washington and the Battle of Fort Erie.
  - 1814 September 2. William Onderdonk ALS to Henry F. Jones; New York., 2 pages; Camp life; "I asure you we presented rather a formidable appearance, we were under arms the whole day & marched about five or six miles…we are now in the service of Uncle Sam…I have been with our company to work & the fortifications at Harlaem; in a short time we expect to have an army of militia in & about this city of nearly twenty five thousand men."
  - 1814 September 10. State of Rhode Island Document to Asahel Hawkins; Gloucester, Rhode Island., 1 pages; Receipt of 57 cents for tax upon Hawkins' property, "under the act of congress passed the 2d August, 1813, to lay and collect a direct tax within the United States."
  - 1814 September 11. Henry Sewall ALS to Samuel Payson; Augusta, [Maine]., 1 page; Troop movements in Maine; he has sent orders for troops to march for Wiscasset and for three regiments to follow them. "On their arrival they will take orders from Gen. Payson or King as the case may be."
  - [post 1814 September 11]. Manuscript poem., 1 page; Poem regarding Thomas Macdonough’s naval victory on Lake Champlain aboard his ship, the Saratoga.
  - 1814 September 12. Thomas Gooding ALS to Eben Parsons; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Discusses people fleeing Boston and the likelihood of British attacking the city; "For my own part I do not fear it for many reasons. The Object is so small (say the destruction of the Navy Yard & the two Ships of War) the British would never be willing to sacrifice 3 or 4000 Men to accomplish it..." If in fact it does occur, he hopes it would not take place for at least 48 hours, in which time they could have the [hulks] sunk.
  - 1814 September 14. Francis L. Coxe ADS; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 1 page; Committee of Defense request to Secretary of the Navy [William Jones] to allow seamen to remain in the city. Also requests guns and ammunition.
  - post 1814 September 14. Manuscript song., 1 page; "The Battel of Baltimore" set to the tune of Yankee Doodle.
  - 1814 September 15. Jacob Wentz DS to David Thomas., 1 page; Orders to march to the Delaware; "you are hereby required personally or by a sufficient substitute, to appear properly armed and equipped…for service, at [Flourtown]…to march immediately for the Delaware."
  - 1814 September 18. Zenas Stebbins DS; Blechertown, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Provision return for company of artillery; includes table of the number of men per rank, number of days, and number of rations.
  - 1814 September 21. Zenas Steebins DS; Blechertown, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Provision return for company of artillery; includes table of the number of men per rank, number of days, and number of rations.
  - 1814 September 22. U.S. Heath ADS to Joseph Hopper Nicholson, 1 page; Orders to attend sermon by Dr. Inglish offering thanks for divine protection in the battle of Baltimore; Inglish had offered his church to officers and delivered a sermon to the 1st Regiment of Artillery. Troops will parade on Washington square.
  - 1814 September 23-November. Ms. receipt, Ms. map, and Ms.; [Pea Patch Island, Delaware]., 3 pages (total); One-page bill for alcohol, food, lodging, horse fodder, captives, drivers, doctors, and others. Includes a pencil manuscript map: "Drawing of 'Peapatch' fortification area on Delaware R in Pa Nov 1814." Also includes a one-page "Draft of proposed fortifications at Pea Patch," describing the architectural processes of creating bastions and expected dimensions.
  - 1814 September 24. Thomas W. Morris ALS to Ann W. Morris; Camp Brandywine., 2 pages; Camp life; he has started his duties as secretary, and "this day received the agreeable intelligence of the victory at Erie the late victories has had a great effect on the Men & sight of the English is anxiously wished for…"
  - 1814 October 2. Henry Denison ALS & 3 Documents to A. Glennie, Son and Co.; Ashburton [London, England]., 8 pages; Speculates on the status of 45 American prisoners on board the Cartel St. Philip, requests an order of clothing for those about to embark. Includes list of supplies for "the supply of Prisoners belonging to the U.S. Navy, about to embark for the U. States in the Cartel St. Philip," including blankets, trousers, and jackets. With three documents with names of Dartmoor prisoners and money and clothing given to them.
  - 1814 October 6. New York State Militia 20th Regiment AD; Sackett’s Harbor, [New York]., 1 page; Payroll for a company of New York Militia commanded by Capt. Ira Hills of the 20th New York Regiment, commanded by Reuben Elinwood.
  - 1814 October 9. John S. Noble DS to John Chaffee; Springfield, [Massachusetts]., 2 pages; Receipt for eleven balls of cannon powder "at the US Arsenal Charlestown."
  - 1814 October 14. B[enjamin] Burton ALS to Lady [Catherine] Burton; Chippawa, Head Quarters, Right Division of the Army, Upper Canada., 3 pages; Lieutenant in the British Army's 19th Light Dragoons writing to his mother in Ireland. Requesting leave, "I should have made the application long since had it not been rarity for the Campaign to break up." Describes battle at Fort Erie on September 17, 1814, as the Americans attempted to break the British siege. "…think we are likely soon to have a nother bloody Battle such as we had at Lundys Lane." Brief mentions of the Battle of Lundy's Lane, Battle of Chippawa, the "storming of Fort Erie," and picket duty. "… although the War has not been much in our favor this Campain there is a very great talk of Peace which every one says must take place before it is long, that Americans must see the folly of keeping up the War."
  - 1814 October 18. Andrew Jackson Cy to William Lauderdale; Mobile, [Alabama]., 3 pages; Orders for the inspection of forts; three forts he will proceed to are Forts Claibourn, Jackson, and Williams.
  - 1814 October 25. Joseph Williamson ALS to Norman Williams; Bangor, [Maine]., 3 pages; Mentions the Battle at Hampden and British invasion. Describes hand picked British invasion force, British officers and the British burning the town on leaving; "great war operations have been going on in the Eastn. Section - operations which have...assailed the interests of individuals & endangered their personal security. The situation of the inhabitants, when the war is brought to their very doors, cannot fail of being more or less distressing."
  - 1814 October 29. G. Wheeler ALS to Mary Wheeler; Harlan Heights, Pennsylvania., 3 pages; Discusses health, camp life; "the Men are getting Sick very fast. The Barracks are so open that we are obliged to send our Sick to the General Hospital…except those that are able to procure themselves private Lodging."
  - 1814 October 29. Maria Ross ALS to George Cockburn; London, [England]., 3 pages; Discusses misfortunes from the war.
  - 1814 October 29. James Monroe LS to Callender Irvine; War Department., 2 pages; Orders to find smuggled goods; "if it should appear that the blankets have been smuggled, you will have them seized." Irvine is to send the Department an estimate of the appropriations his department will need for the coming year.
  - 1814 October 29. U.S. Army General Hospital DS; Baltimore, [Maryland]., 1 page; Order for five cords of firewood.
  - 1814 November 4. Samuel Ranlet DS to; Edgecomb, [Massachusetts]., 2 pages; Muster roll for the Massachusetts company of artillery under Captain Samuel Ranlet.; Located in Oversize Manuscripts.
  - 1814 November 8. George Wilson DS., 1 page; Account certifying that Wilson delivered the items listed (rations of pork, flour, and whiskey) to Antoine Boidon, "Patronizing the said James Morrisons Boat loaded with provisions destined for the Port of France…"
  - 1814 November 11. New York State Militia 20th Regiment. Pr. Document & 2 ADs., 4 pages; Muster roll and pay receipt under Capt. Ira Hills; includes notes on deserters and those discharged. Folder includes two pay receipt rolls for the regiment.
  - 1814 November 15. United States Army ADS to Col. Fisk; Portsmouth, [New Hampshire]., 1 page; Military discharge, orders by Brigade Major James [Swan] which include paroling McDonough.
  - 1814 November 18. Sir George Prevost LS to Sir Gordon Drummond; Montreal, [Quebec]., 2 pages; Military strategy against General McArthur, hopes of setting up American troops as prey to Indian attacks, orders to burn American mills; "I am in hopes the force under General McArthur will…fall a sacrifice to the exertions of the Indians supported, as I trust they will have been by every possible assistance..." Because the Americans have destroyed British mills, he orders Drummond to "direct the Troops under your Command no longer to abstain...from burning the Mills in the Enemy's Country..."
  - 1814 November 23. Joseph McGavock ALS to Hugh McGavock; Camp near Buffalo., 3 pages; Discusses his company's involvement in the Battle at Chippewa, summarizes the Niagara Campaign. He recounts a duel; "there was a Duel fought yesterday between Doct Dade of the tenth, and Capt James Paxton, of the twelveth, Dade was Killed Dead on the spot, and Capt Paxton Mortally wounded through the body."
  - 1814 December 17. Charles Carroll ALS to Robert G[oodloe] Harper; Baltimore, [Maryland]., 2 pages; Hopes to see a body of troops raised by the state; "It is much to be desired to have a body of regular troops raised by the State for its defence but I fear the means will be wanting to raise and pay a competent number."
  - 1814 December 22. John Coffee DS; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 1 page; Order to pay $8 for an express rider to take dispatches to Maj. Gen. [Andrew] Jackson. Includes confirmation stating that "The above Services were performed as charged and aught to be paid." Includes receipt dated February 22, 1815, stating that the $8 was received in full.
  - 1814 December 23. William King ALS to Henry Dearborn; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 3 pages; Regarding troop movements and militia.
  - 1814 December 30. Lt. Blackshear ALS to John McIntosh; Camp on Oakmulgee Creek., 2 pages; Discusses marching, during which he detached two companies to clear a road and make a bridge.
  - [1814 to 1815]. 2 Manuscript notebooks., 33 pages; Two notebooks about United States privateers and warships; one is nine pages in length, the other is twenty four. The nine-page manuscript is entitled, "A Journal of Privateers & U.S. vessels That Sailed from the United States In 1814 or a part of them."
  - 1814. Committee of British Merchants Document., 55 pages; Letter, minutes, and a printed appendix addressed to Sir George Prevost. The minutes suggest new boundaries and provide suggestions pertaining to American forts and vessels.
  - 1814. Connecticut Adjutant General’s orders Pr. Document; Connecticut., 1 page; Broadside announcing that the captain general "is informed that doubts are entertained" whether officers of the militia are allowed to discharge commissioned officers; he believes that late Governor Trumbull's orders delegating this authority to the General Officers have not been revoked. He reminds officers of the stipulations under which discharges are acceptable. Includes writing from Ebenezer Huntington regarding returns of militia and list of [officer's] names that need to be sent to his office.
  - 1814. 4 Documents., 7 pages; Receipts.
  - [post 1814]. Unknown AL to Unknown., 4 pages; Incomplete account of an individual’s military exploits during the War of 1812, including the Battle of Sackett’s Harbor. Born in Pennsylvania in 1786, the writer includes a brief autobiography. He joined the army as a 2nd lieutenant in the 15th Infantry under Col. Pike.
  - 1815 January 2. George Washington Campbell ADfS to John Armstrong; Nashville, [Tennessee]., 3 pages; Comments on economic situation, the destruction of naval forces near New Orleans; "Our gun boats on the lakes near N. Orleans have been taken or [destroyed]…Will England make peace, if not…by the result of the Congress at Vienna?" He requests to information on political affairs. (Box 5)
  - 1815 January 9. Joseph S. Winter ALS to Elisha I. Winter; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 7 pages; Discusses the Battle of New Orleans; "The British yesterday made a grand assault upon our Works and were repulsed with a most unprecedented loss on their side of killed & wounded & there is an armistice until 12 o'clock today for them to bury their dead…"